Edward Devereux papers
Devereux, Edward papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Edward Devereux papers, ca.1936-1978
23-13-3191
Edward Clifton Devereux.
3.4 cubic feet.
Correspondence, publications, course material, subject files.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, publications, course material and subject files pertaining to Devereux's interest in the ways families are organized cross-culturally and historically and how these variations affect child rearing, with reference to these subjects in Japan, Germany, Israel and England. Also files on gambling, the juvenile courts in Tompkins County, children's games, in particular Little League, and correspondence concerning his documentary film "Two Ball Games."
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Edward Devereux was Professor of Human Development and Human Studies at Cornell University from 1950-1978.
Edward Devereux was born in Long Island, New York in 1912. He received his A.B. and Ph.D. degrees in Sociology from Harvard in 1940. After two years as a Sociology Instructor at the University of Toronto, Devereux entered the U.S. Navy as a navigator and executive officer on a fleet tanker until 1945. He was then appointed Assistant Professor of Sociology at Princeton for five years, before joining the Cornell University faculty as Associate Professor of Child Development and Family Studies in 1950, serving as Department Chair from 1966-1970.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, publications, course material and subject files pertaining to Devereux's interest in the ways families are organized cross-culturally and historically and how these variations affect child rearing, with reference to these subjects in Japan, Germany, Israel and England. Also files on gambling, the juvenile courts in Tompkins County, children's games, in particular Little League, and correspondence concerning his documentary film "Two Ball Games."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Devereux, Edward Clifton.; Devereux, Edward Clifton.; Cornell University-- Faculty.; New York State College of Human Ecology-- Department of Human Development and Family Studies.; Tompkins County (N.Y.)Youth Court.
Titles:
Last Resort.
Subjects:
Juvenile Courts--New York (State)--Tompkins County.; Gambling--Social aspects--United States.; Horse racing--Betting--United States.; Children--Japan.; Child abuse--United States--Periodicals.; Children--Israel.; Children--Germany.; Children--England.; Child rearing.; Child development.; Children--United States.; (Little League) baseball.
Places:
Candor (N.Y.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 1, folders 20-22 are restricted until 2026, folder 51 is restricted until 2046 at which time the restrictions will be reevaluated.
RELATED MATERIAL
A DVD of the two copies of the film "Two Ball Games" can be found in collection #21-36-2566, box 24
SERIES LIST
Series I. AT & T Company
Box 1, Folders 1-5
Series II. Springdale - Community Study
Box 1, Folders 6-25
Series III. Germany - Study
Box 1, Folders 26-30
Series IV. Series IV. Israel - Study
Box 1, Folders 31-41
Series V. Hawaii - Study
Box 1, Folders 42-44
Series VI. Japan - Study
Box 1, Folders 45-54
Series VII. Course Material
Box 2, Folders 1-29
Series VIII. Seminars/Conferences
Box 2, Folders 30-42
Series IX. Publications
Box 3, Folders 1-57A
Series X. Subject Files: Children's Play
Box 3, Folders 58-67
Series XI. Subject Files: Gambling
Box 4, Folders 1-12
Series XII. Projects
Box 4, Folders 13-15
Series XIII. Biographical material and Correspondence
Box 4, Folders 16-20
Series XIV. Talks and Sound Recordings
Box 4, Folders 21-22
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. AT & T Company - Study
  - Drafts of various chapters for publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Invisible Competitors of Social Research-drafts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interviews with AT and T employees, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Applied Social Sciences Research - Vol. 1, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Applied Social Sciences Research - Vol. 1- research and comments, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. Springdale - Community Study
  - Code book, various cards (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Social sensitivity, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Participation Deviance, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 10-forms of community involvement and participation (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Community survey pre-test items, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Variables in survey (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Community problems analysis (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Neighborhood classifications, coding key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 4- The People of Springdale: Background Characteristics (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ecological material and chapter on Civic Awareness (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Organizations, summary of data, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cornell community survey (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sample background data, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cornell Research Program in Candor, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Field Notes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Field Notes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Field Notes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Staff document files- A long-range program of research on the detriments of constructive social behavior, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Staff document files - A long-range program of research on the detriments of constructive social behavior, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Papers by Carlfred Broderick - Nature and Role of Informal Family Groups, Social Integration in Springdale and Urban Conjugal Family and the Social Mechanisms which Support and Stabilize It, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series III. Germany - Study
  - Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Family Authority Structure and Child Behavior-key and remarks, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Questionnaires (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence - Frankfurt, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Parental Behavior and Family Structure in West Germany" -results of analyses of variance for nine parent behavior factors, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series IV. Israel - Study
  - Parent Behavior Instruments, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Research proposal - Studies of Group Upbringing, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Research proposal - Cross-Cultural Studies of Child Rearing, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cross-Cultural Studies, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Research proposal - Family Structure and Personality Development, 1958, 1962, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Research proposal - Cross-Cultural Studies of Socialization, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Research proposal - Cross-Cultural Studies of Family Behavior, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Research Project - Sociological Studies of the Family, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Research Project - Changing Structure of the Rural Community with Implications for Rural Programming, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Occupational Roles and Parent-Child Relationships, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series V. Hawaii - Study
  - Honolulu - pilot study, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Honolulu-Semantic Differential (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hawaii - pre-test forms (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series VI. Japan - Study
  - Family Structure, Socialization Settings and Child Behavior Outcomes in Japan - code book, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Report and correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence concerning travel arrangements, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Expenses, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Pre-test and parent interviews (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Questionnaires (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Long form (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Student paper - A Trend of Parent Behavior and Family Authority Structure in Three Cultures - by Edward Gubman, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Series VII. Course material
  - Various course material, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Research Methods in Child Development and Family Relations" CDFR), 1950-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Child Development and Family Relations" 501-502, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "DFR and Human Development and Family Studies"(HDFS), 1955-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Family and Society", 1958, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Family in Cross-Cultural Perspective", 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Family, Kinship and Society" - 543 and 564 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Family Relationships and the Social Structure" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "American Family"- talks, article, course material, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Family-CDFR 406 and sample student paper, bibliography, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Family Life in the United States - some area studies in the role of the father in the family, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Experimental Methods - lectures, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jewish Family - Israeli Family, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Homan's theory, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Technology and the Social Values of Industrialism", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Studies of Marital Success, 1950-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Psychopathology, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Old age retirement (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dating and Courtship, 1950-1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Assortative Mating and Intermarriage, 1950-1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - China - family systems, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kinship systems - Ireland, French Canadian, 1942-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ecology project - with Bronfenbrenner and Cochran, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Course outline - Social Disorganization (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Class papers by Devereux Study of Harvard-Radcliffe students, 1938-1939, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sociology - Harvard-handwritten notes, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sociology - participant observation guides (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Case studies in delinquency and crime- Douglas, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Znaniecki-method of sociology- notes (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series VIII. Seminars/Conferences
  - Conferences participated in by Devereux, 1965, 1967, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Seminar on Talcott Parsons, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Seminar on Talcott Parsons, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Talcott Parsons' Group" Minutes Correspondence with Norb Wiley, 1936-1937, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - American Civilization - conference at Princeton, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - The Role of the "Elite" in American Civilization- conference at Princeton, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Development of Moral Sense in Children - symposium, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Research Perspectives in the Ecology of Human Development - conference at Cornell, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Papers presented at above Human Development conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Papers presented at Human Development conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Papers presented at Human Development conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Papers presented at Human Development conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Papers presented at Human Development conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Series IX. Publications
  - Child Development - editorial, correspondence, revisions, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Psychological Ecology: A Critical Analysis and Appraisal - correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - On Children's Games: Adult Organized vs. Child-Organized - a guide to accompany Two Ball Games, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Backyard versus Little League Baseball: The Impoverishment of Children's Games, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Socialization Practices of Parents, Teachers and Peers in Israel Children of Immigrants from Eastern and Western Nations - by Devereux and others, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Socialization Practices of Parents, Teachers, and Peers in Israel: The Kibbutz versus the City- by Devereux and others, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Protocol for Structural-Functional Analysis, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Models for Man, Value Systems and Intervention Strategies: A Sociological Critique of Wolpe and Jourand, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Adolescent Male Initiation Ceremonies: A Structured-Functional Analysis, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Structural-Functional Analysis: A Protocol Based on Works of Parsons, Merton, Kingsley, Davis, Malinowski and others, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Some Observations on the Changing Family and the Role of Education in the People's Republic of China, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Some Antecedents and Correlates of Differential Patterns of Response to pressures from Peers and Adults Among Israeli Kibbutz Children, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Social Contexts, Family Relationships and the Moral Development of Children, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Physiology and Psychology of Sport - Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women Conference, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - How I Learned to Use a Lever, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Authority and Moral Development Among German and American Children: A Cross-National Pilot Experiment, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Some Reflections on Research Reporting in Psychology, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Backyard versus Little League Baseball: The Impoverishment of Children's Games, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Soziologie der Familie, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Role of Peer-Group Experience in Moral Development, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Child-Rearing in England and the U.S.- A Cross-National Comparison -by Devereux and others, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Standards of Social Behavior Among School Children in Four Cultures, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Authority, Guilt and Conformity to Adult Standards Among German Children: A Pilot Experimental Study, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Socialization in Cross-Cultural Perspective: A Comparative Study of England, Germany and the U.S., 1965 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Family Relationships and the Formation of the Ability to Build Up Human and Social Relationships and The Role of the Family in Youth Education-UNESCO talk, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Families in East and East, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Adults and Peers as Sources of Conformity and Autonomy- by Devereux and others, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - The Tompkins County Youth Court, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Pre-Adolescents- Why Is Each One Different?, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - A Brief Survey of the Family in Contemporary America, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Patterns of Parent Behavior in the U.S. and the Federal Republic of Germany: A Cross-National Comparison-by Devereux and others, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Mercurio- L'allevamento die figli in Germania e negli, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Family Authority and Child Behavior in West Germany and the U.S. -Some Problems and Strategies in a Cross-National Validation Study, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Children of Democracy, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Child Rearing in America and Germany- A Cross-National Comparison, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Family Authority Structure and Adolescent Behavior, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Adolescents and Family Structure -address given at Leadership Training Conference, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Forms of Community Involvement and Participation - Springdale - Chapter 10, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Neighborhood and Community Participation - A study of the Social Ecology of a Rural Community - Springdale, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - The World of the Adolescent, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Interdisciplinary Planning for Team Research on Constructive Community Behavior - the Springdale Project - Devereux and Bronfenbrenner, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Some Formal Characteristics of Rational and Non-rational Action, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Sociology and Labour Relations - lecture given at University of Toronto, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - The Place of Human Ecology in the Science of Criminology, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Some Reflections on the Methods and Theories of John Dollard's Caste and Class in a Southern Town, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Standards of Social Behavior Among School Children in Four Cultures - by Devereux Technical Report on a Measure of Anxiety and Self-Esteem; Changes in Parental Behavior Reported by Children in W. Germany and the U.S. - by Robert Rodgers, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - The Sociological Theory of Talcott Parsons: An Introductory Overview (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - The Individual Delinquent of William Healy as a Study in Causal Analysis (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Occupational Roles and Parent-Child Relationships - research proposal - Bronfenbrenner and Devereux (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Research Proposals and correspondence, 1964-1978 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Book Reviews - Influences on Parent Behavior; The Japanese Factory: Aspects of its Social Organization; The Kibbutz Experience, 1967, 1958, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Articles, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Speech given to Home Economics Council-"Cross-Cultural Research on Family Structure and Personality Development", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Reviews, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Poem (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Harold Feldman-publications, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Newspaper clippings on spanking/discipline, 1960-1979 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Gilbertsville Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 57A)
  - The Last Resort - newsletter of the Committee to End Violence Against the Next Generation - Berkeley, CA., 1981-1994 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
- Series X. Subject Files: Children's Play
  - Little League Studies, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Devereux papers on this topic, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - A response to "Two Ball Games" - by Stephen Mosher from SUNY Brockport and Play, Games and Sport in Human Development by Douglas Kleiber from Cornell, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "Two Ball Games" - film project - proposal -how the project developed, 1974, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - "Two Ball Games" - background material, press releases, articles, correspondence, 1976, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - "Two Ball Games" - correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - "Two Ball Games" - correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "Two Ball Games" - correspondence, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - "Two Ball Games" - correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Children's Play Conference, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Series XI. Subject Files: Gambling
  - Publications (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Racing-Gambling - catalogs and advertisements (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Draft of chapter on number players - comments by RK Merton (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Economic and Non-Economic Elements in Gambling: An Essay in the Field of Psychological and Institutional Economics (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Ethical Status of Gambling in American Society (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sample of field notes - interviews, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Papers presented at 2nd annual Conference on Gambling, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gambling in Psychological and Sociological Perspective, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - World Book Encyclopedia entry on Gambling, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gambling and the Social Structure - Table of Contents, Abstract (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence concerning thesis, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Encyclopedia of Social Sciences entry on Gambling, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series XII. Projects
  - Grant Project - Tompkins County Demonstration Project, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Articles concerning project done in Windsor, CT., 1937 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Article about project done in Surrey, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series XIII. Biographical material and Correspondence
  - Vita, Correspondence, Articles, 1967-1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Reflections on the draft, the energy crisis, and family life (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Vietnam War - packet and letters, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series XIV. Talks and Sound Recordings
  - Gilbertsville Radio Talk, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Criminology- radio talk, notes, course outlines, 1936-1948 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Permisiveness vs. Control"- sound recording (2 copies), 1964; SR-1120